- Thank you Eric for leading us the songs to worship God.
(speaking in foreign language)
And today I would like to bring you a short series
on I believe and understanding the creeds
in church history.
(speaking in foreign language)
If someone asks you, okay, if someone asks you,
if someone asks you what is the Christian faith
is all about, okay, your neighbor or your friend
or your un-church friend, can you, can you explain
what Christian faith is all about?
You know, in a summarized fashion, you know.
How do you explain it with some clarity
what this Christian faith is all about?
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, can you?
Okay, all right, we see an amen there, okay.
Other people are pretty humble, I guess.
(speaking in foreign language)
So can you explain?
So life is a progress, okay?
Your life is a progress and the Christian life
is also a progress.
You cannot stay like a baby all the time.
You have to grow.
You have to grow up and you have to become more experienced
and you cannot just stop right at where you're at.
And Christian life is like that.
(speaking in foreign language)
So the question is, are you making progress
in your Christian faith journey?
(speaking in foreign language)
So, but first of all, no one can understand
or comprehend the Bible, everything about the Bible.
But the simple message of the gospel is easy to understand.
And to really comprehend the whole Bible is no easy task.
I've been reading the Bibles for so many years
and I still have something puzzling when I read the Bible.
But creeds, C-R-E-E-D, creeds serve the purpose
of summarizing the essentials of Christian faith.
(speaking in foreign language)
So what is creed?
What is creed?
Creed comes from the Latin word, credo,
and then evolves into Old English creda.
And then the basic meaning, meaning I believe.
(speaking in foreign language)
So, before we look at the historical creeds,
you need to understand when you read the Bible,
sometimes you bump into some creed-like statement
in the Bible.
And let me give you an example.
And the example is 1 Corinthians 15,
and I'll let the translator first before I read that verse.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, let me read the passage.
Okay, 1 Corinthians 15, first of all in English.
"Now, brethren and sisters, I want you to remind you
"of the gospel I preached to you, which you receive
"and on which you have taken your stand.
"By this gospel, you are saved
"if you hold firmly to the word I preached to you.
"Otherwise, you have believed in vain.
"For I receive, I pass on to you
"as of first importance that Christ died for our sins
"according to the scriptures, that he was buried,
"that he was raised on the third day
"according to the scriptures,
"and that he appeared to Peter and then to the twelfth."
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, pay attention to, for I deliver to you
as of first importance what I also believe.
Now, that comes from probably an earlier document
or earlier Christian creed-like statements
and something that Paul himself had received
before he wrote this letter,
and now he's writing this letter
and passing on to the church.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, notice also the statements are very simple and short.
Christ died, and Christ was buried,
Christ was raised from the dead,
and then Christ appeared to the apostles.
And death, it talks about the burial of Christ,
his death, his resurrection, the witness,
and that is an early Christian creed or summary
found inside the Bible.
Now, before the church come up with creeds, summaries,
the Christians in Bible time are already summarizing
the heart of their faith in very short statements
and easy to be remembered, easy to be repeated,
and to be passed on.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, as we all know, in the early church history,
especially the first 300 years,
now, as you can see, the time of the New Testament
end at the end of first century AD.
And then for the first 300 years,
the churches often live under pressure
and suffering and persecution.
And then around the end of the first century AD,
the churches are living under the pressure
and suffering and persecution, and then around AD 300,
Constantine, that is the defining moment of world history,
he became a Christian and then he's legalized Christianity.
And then Constantine shifted center of his government
from Rome to Constantinople, which is today Istanbul.
His shift his center over there and made it his new capital.
(speaking in foreign language)
So after AD 312, the church from suffering
and they came up to the surface, it became public.
And then they got greater freedom and what did they do?
They gather and then they debate
and they try to clarify their faith.
So there were many controversies happening
in the past 300 years.
And now the church could have the space
to work through all these questions,
especially essential questions.
And so, as you can see,
you work through all these questions, especially essential
questions, who is Jesus and is he truly God
or is he truly human?
(speaking in foreign language)
So then there were many great church creeds
that emerged out of the councils.
And this table shows you some of the major ones,
some of the major summaries or creeds
of the faith of the Christian faith.
(speaking in foreign language)
So on the upper left, there is apostles' creed.
Anyone remember that?
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, sometimes we use it in baptism.
And then upper right, about AD 325,
there was another council and they came up
with the creed called Nicene Creed.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then lower left, and then some years later, 381 AD,
and they came up with another creed
called Constantinople Creed.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then some years later, there's another creed
because they try to clarify some other issues
called Chalcedon Creed.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, as you can see in this table,
apostles' creed is a very quick summary of the core beliefs.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then that's apostles' creed.
But the second one is the Nicene Creed.
Nicene Creed try to clarify the question, who Jesus is,
because there was a cult called Arianism
and they are infiltrating the church.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then lower left, Constantinople Creed,
they try to clarify the divinity
or the deity of Holy Spirit.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then lower right,
and there's another controversy coming up
is how to clarify Jesus Christ being fully God
and fully human, and how do we communicate that?
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, those are very important creeds
and we're gonna go through them later.
(speaking in foreign language)
But first of all, you need to understand
there were some benefits of knowing the creeds,
understanding the creeds of the church history.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, there are at least five benefits
we can get from understanding the creeds.
First of all, you understand the creed, the summary,
then you hold on to the core beliefs,
the core truth of faith.
And then second one is that the creeds tell you
what is essential and what is secondary in our faith, okay?
Number three is that the creeds are to protect us
from serious theological errors.
And number four, reciting the creeds,
understanding the creeds.
We have fellowship or we have communion
with believers of all times, all ages.
And then number five, the creeds will renew our faith
by bringing us back to who God truly is
and who Jesus really is.
(speaking in foreign language)
So as we recite the creed today, when we say, I believe,
and I want you to understand it's not just in your head.
It's that I believe when I say that I believe in God,
I will worship God and him alone.
And I will continue to seek his will
in all decisions in my life because he is the God,
he is the Lord.
(speaking in foreign language)
So today, I would like to do something that we rarely do,
is to recite one of the creeds.
(speaking in foreign language)
So the creed that we're gonna begin with
is, of course, the apostles' creed.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then we're gonna recite it in English first
and then in Chinese later.
(speaking in foreign language)
But as we do that, I want you to understand
when I say I believe, you know, I invest my life in God.
(speaking in foreign language)
And when I say, I believe in God,
I entrust my life to God.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, so shall we recite it today?
Okay, why don't we all stand up?
You know, according to ancient tradition,
we stand up and we recite the creed.
(speaking in foreign language)
So let's do it in English first and then Chinese.
Apostle's creed.
I believe in God, the Father Almighty,
creator of heaven and earth.
I believe in Jesus Christ, his only Son, our Lord.
He was conceived by the power of the Holy Spirit
and born of the Virgin Mary.
He suffered under Pontius Pilate,
was crucified, died, and was buried.
He descended to the dead.
On the third day, he rose again.
He ascended into heaven
and is seated at the right hand of the Father.
He will come again to judge the living and the dead.
I believe in the Holy Spirit,
the holy universal church,
the communion of saints,
the forgiveness of sins,
the resurrection of the body,
and the life everlasting, amen.
(speaking in foreign language)
Let's all pray together.
Father, we give you thanks because you are our God.
(speaking in foreign language)
And thank you, your Son has done so much in our lives.
Because of Jesus Christ, your Son.
(speaking in foreign language)
We have eternal life.
And help us to worship you.
(speaking in foreign language)
Help us to see you as our true Lord in our life.
And help us to know you and follow your will.
(speaking in foreign language)
In Jesus' name we pray.
Amen.
(speaking in foreign language)
Well, today we don't have the announcement
because the most important announcement of all
is that we are going to the aquarium.
(speaking in foreign language)
And that's why we wanna end a little bit earlier.
So you grab something to eat.
(speaking in foreign language)
And head out to the bus and to aquarium and have a good time.
I'm very pleased because some of you
are bringing your friends.
(speaking in foreign language)
Because that is the intent of programs like this.
We wanna reach out to other people
and bring them to church.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, amen?
- Amen. - Yeah.
And also I wanna remind you the expansion fund is growing.
(speaking in foreign language)
Our goal is by the end of this year,
we're gonna raise 100K.
(speaking in foreign language)
And so far we already have more than 50%, right?
Amen to that. - Amen.
So invest in the church, right?
(speaking in foreign language)
Invest in God.
And God bless you.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, see you in the aquarium or next week.
Okay, God bless you.
(speaking in foreign language)